Guide to the Winkler Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence
  - LETTERS TO WINKLER
    - Schnorr von Carolsfeld, Julius, 1794-1872. ALS, Dresden, 1854 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 90)
      1 p. Artist; from 1846 on director of the gallery of fine arts at Dresden; son of Veit Hans Schnorr von Carolsfeld. Requesting the loan of a medieval garment for the use of Mr. Tom Dieck for the execution of a painting
    - Schoppe, Amalia Emma Sophie Katherine (Weise), 1791-1858. ALS, Hamburg, 1822 Sep 25 (Box 2, Folder 91)
      1 p. Prolific writer, editor of the Taschenbuch Cornelia; emigrated to America in 1851 to join her son in Schenectady. Concerning fees due her from contributions to the periodical Die Muse
    - Schreyvogel, Josef, 1768-1832. ALS, Wien, 1817 Feb 1 (Box 2, Folder 92)
      4 p. Concerns his contributions to the Abendzeitung, especially in regard to his play Donna Diana; recommends Grillparzer on the strength of his Die Ahnfrau
    - Schützke, Johann Stephan 1771-1839. ALS, Weimar, 1820 Sep 13 (Box 2, Folder 93)
      1 p. Editor of almanacs and an associate of Goethe. Submitting a contribution on the theory of the comic for the Abendzeitung
    - Seefried, Sidonie Freiin von. ALS, Buttenheim bei Bamberg, 1826 Apr 30 (Box 2, Folder 94)
      3 p. Asking his opinion as to the quality of her poetry
    - Smidt, Heinrich, 1798-1867. 2 ALS, Berlin; Altona, 1825-26 (Box 2, Folder 95)
      4 p. Concerns publication of his early works in the Abendzeitung
    - Starklof, Karl Christian Ludwig, 1789-1850. ALS, Oldenberg, 1835 Oct 5 (Box 2, Folder 96)
      3 p. Cabinet secretary and manager of the new theater at Oldenberg. Acknowledges receipt of three comedies and requests information concerning acquisition of the score for the opera Yelva
    - Stepanek, Jan Nepomuk, 1783-1844. ALS, Prag, 1825 May 27 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      1 p. Dramatist, theater director and editor of the Tschechische Prager Zeitung, he was called the "Tschechische Kotzebue." Concerns guest engagement of the actor Heine and Winkler's adaption of Hamlet
    - Sturm & Koppe, firm. 2 ALS, Leipzig, 1841-45 (Box 2, Folder 98)
      2 p. The second letter is on stationery with the heading Das Theatergeschäftsbureau und Die Redaktion der Allgemeinen Theater-Chronik von Sturm and Koppe, Leipzig
    - Teichman, Johann Valentin, 1791-1860. ALS, Berlin, 1821 Jun 5 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      1 p. Member of the "Generalintendantur der Königlichen Schauspiele, Berlin." Chiefly concerns the opera Alcidor
    - Tieck, Friedrich, 1776-1851. ALS, Berlin, 1825 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 100)
      3 p. Sculptor. Chiefly concerning an article on the sculptor Christian Daniel Rauch
    - Tieck, Johann Ludwig, 1773-1853. ALS (Box 2, Folder 101)
      1 p. Promising the beginning of a manuscript
    - Timroth, Henriette von. ALS, Schmogerau bei Winzig, 1826 Jun 21 (Box 2, Folder 102)
      4 p. Concerns the manuscripts of certain of her works, to be submitted for publication in the Abendzeitung or one of Winkler's almanacs; includes a biographical sketch of her father
    - Tittmann, Friedrich Wilhelm, 1784-1864. ALS, Dresden, 1825 Sep 7 (Box 2, Folder 103)
      1 p. Archivist at the "Hauptstaatsarchiv" at Dresden. Offering reminiscences on Prague for publication in the Abendzeitung
    - Urban, Wilhelm, 1795-1833. ALS, München, 1826 Apr 21 (Box 2, Folder 104)
      3 p. Actor at the court theater in München. Concerns an adverse criticism by Mr. Behr in the Abendzeitung
    - Vaerst, Friedrich Christian Eugen, Freiherr von, 1792-1855. ALS, Breslau, 1841 Sep 21 (Box 2, Folder 105)
      1 p. Editor of the Breslauer Zeitung; director of the Breslauer Theater. Requesting a copy of Winkler's comedy Liebe und Liebelei. Letter mutilated; portion below signature cut
    - Vogler, Heinrich Friedrich Magnus, 1785-1857. ALS, 1826 Apr 16 (Box 2, Folder 106)
      5 p. Concerns chiefly the publication of his novel Der Schützenhof zu Osterburg in the Abendzeitung, and some reviews of his Das Feuerwerk
    - Vulpius, Christian August, 1762-1827. 2 ALS, Weimar, 1800-20 (Box 2, Folder 107)
      2 p.
    - Weber, Carl Gottlieb von, 1773-1849. ALS, Dresden, 1825 Feb 26 (Box 2, Folder 108)
      2 p. Writer on church law, member of the committee for the support of orphans; he was ennobled in 1828. Thanking for a donation from the proceeds of the performance of the play Paria at various German theaters, for the benefit of the Waisenanstalt at Pirna
    - Weber, Karl Maria Friedrich Ernst, freiherr von, 1786-1826. ALS, 1824 Jul 7 (Box 2, Folder 109)
      1 p. Relates to performances of his Euryanthe at Weimar
    - Wendt, Amadeus, 1783-1836. 2 ALS, Leipzig, 1825 Feb 24 (Box 2, Folder 110)
      4 p. Professor of philosophy at Leipzig, later at Göttingen; writer of criticism of art from the philosophical view point; editor of Taschenbuch zum Geselligen Vergnügen and Deutscher Musenalmanach
    - Witzleben, Karl August Friedrich von, 1773-1839. ALS, Berlin, 1822 Feb 4 (Box 2, Folder 111)
      1 p. Submitting a poem and a play in verse and promising a short story for publication
    - Wohlbrück, Gustav Friedrich, 1793-1849. ALS, Königsberg, 1825 Aug 17 (Box 2, Folder 112)
      2 p. Actor and stage manager
    - Zöllner. 2 ALS, Ludwigslust, 1836-37 (Box 2, Folder 113)
      6 p.
    - Zschokke, Heinrich, 1771-1848. ALS, Aaru, Switzerland, 1832 Sep 20 (Box 2, Folder 114)
      8 p. Relates to the government reforms in Switzerland
  - LETTERS TO ELISA VON DER RECKE
    - Berenhorst, Georg Heinrich von, 1733-1814. ALS, Dessau, 1796 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 115)
      2 p. Adjutant to Prince Heinrich and later Frederic II of Prussia; became Hofmarschall and retired to Dresden. Discusses the illness and subsequent death of his daughter Eugenia
    - Blumenbach, Johann Friedrich, 1752-1840. ALS, Göttingen, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 116)
      2 p. Anthropologist and physician
    - Conta, Karl Friedrich Anton von, 1778-1850. ALS, Weimar, 1823 Mar 12 (Box 2, Folder 117)
      3 p. "Grossherzoglich Sächsischer Landes-Directions-Präsident"; friend of Goethe. Discusses Goethe's grave illness earlier in the year
    - Demme, Hermann Christian Gottfried, 1760-1822 2 ALS, Altenburg, 1816-20 (Box 2, Folder 118)
      7 p. General superintendent and Consistorialrath in charge of church and school affairs in the Duchy Altenburg; author of devotional works and hymns
    - Feuerbach, Paul Johann Anselm Ritter von, 1775-1833. ALS, Ansbach, 1825 Jul 26 (Box 2, Folder 119)
      4 p. The letter was probably written by a secretary cf. Allgemeine Deutsche Biographie, v.6; p.738
    - Gagen, Christiane von. ALS, Stöberg, 1785 Apr 25 (Box 2, Folder 120)
      2 p. Requesting a meeting to make EVDR's acquaintance
    - Gleim, Johann Wilhelm Ludewig, 1719-1803. ALS, Halberstadt, 1787 Mar 10 (Box 2, Folder 121)
      3 p. Expressing elation at the birth of a son to the Duchess of Curland, the sister of EVDR
    - Gramberg. ALS, Valencay, 1822 Aug 31 (Box 2, Folder 122)
      4 p. Chiefly relates to the Duchess Dorothée de Sagan (died 1862); with mention of Tiedge
    - Himmel, Friedrich Heinrich, 1765-1814. ALS, Wein, 1812 Jan 15 (Box 2, Folder 123)
      6 p. Composer; acquainted with Goethe
    - Holtey, Johann Dietrich von. ALS, Satticken, 1822 Mar 21 (Box 2, Folder 124)
      3 p.
    - Hüttner, Christian Gottlieb von, 1787-1854. ALS, Leipzig, 1824 Nov 11 (Box 2, Folder 125)
      4 p. Postmaster General for Saxony. Chiefly relates to her article on the subject of life and death
    - Katter. ALS, Hamburg, 1809 Mar 25 (Box 2, Folder 126)
      7 p. Chiefly about the death of his wife
    - Klinger, Friedrich Maximilian von, 1752-1831. 2 ALS, St. Petersburg, 1796-1815 (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Körner, Christian Gottfried, 1756-1831. 2 ALS, Grossenhayn; Ludwigslust, 1813-14 (Box 2, Folder 128)
      7 p. These two letters relate to the death of Körner's son Theodor, and a pilgrimage to his grave and the erection of a monument at Wöbbelin near Ludwigslust
    - Krug, Wilhelm Traugott, 1770-1842. ALS, Leipizig, 1829 Jan 14 (Box 2, Folder 129)
      3 p. A philosopher. Thanking for a collecting subscribers for a work he is preparing for the publisher Vieweg
    - Mariia Pavlovna, Grand Duchess of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach, 1786-1859. ALS, Weimar, 1823 Jan 26 (Box 2, Folder 130)
      1 p. Written by a secretary; signed: Maria Grossfürstin von Russland, Erbgrossherzogin zu Sachsen. Thanking for a copy of Johann Gottlieb Naumann's composition to Klopstock's Vaterunser
    - Meissner, August Gottlieb, 1753-1807. ALS, Prag, 1799 Feb 18 (Box 2, Folder 131)
      4 p. Compares Klinger's Weltmann und Dichter favorably to Wilhelm Meister; mentions his own work Leben des Julius Caesar
    - Motz, Friedrich Christian Adolf von, 1775-1830. ALS, Fulda, 1808 Feb 20 (Box 2, Folder 132)
      7 p. Chiefly relates to forwarding the literary remains of their mutual friend August Gottlieb Meissner
    - An Lyde [poem] signed: Mssr. ALS, Teplitz, 1804 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 133)
      2 p. Begins: Freudin, Klage nicht des Lebens. Lyde probably is EVDR. The manuscript was found together with 3 poems by K.A. Böttiger to Elisa von der Recke.
    - Naumann, Catina (von Grodtschilling) ALS, Dresden, 1800 Apr 28 (Box 2, Folder 134)
      4 p. With postscript by her husband Johann Gottlieb Naumann. ALS to her daughter "Röschen" who is visiting with EVDR
    - Naumann, Johann Gottlieb, 1741-1801. 3 ALS, Blasewitz, 1798, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 135)
      8 p. The letter of 1798 relates chiefly to his compositions to EVDR poems
    - Reimarus, Elise. ALS, Hamburg, 1799 Jul 13 (Box 2, Folder 136)
    - Reinhard, Franz Volkmar, 1753-1812. ALS (Box 2, Folder 137)
      3 p. Thanking for condolences received at the death of his mother
    - Rudolphi, Karoline Christiane Louise Died 1811. ALS, Hamburg, 1796 Oct 7 (Box 2, Folder 138)
      4 p. Educator and writer of works on education. A volume of her poems was published in 1781
    - Stock, Dorothea, 1760?-1832. ALS, Berlin, 1814 Apr 13 (Box 2, Folder 139)
      4 p. Painter; lived in the house of her brother-in-law Christian Gottfried Körner
  - LAVATER-VON DER RECKE
    - Lavater, Johann Caspar, 1741-1801. Autograph MSS. 23 items., 1781-89 (Box 2, Folder 140)
      Correspondence with Eliza von- der Recke chiefly relating to Cagliostro. With handwritten transcripts of his Manifest, copies of letters to von Blankenberg, and copies of letters from C.F. Nicolai, all relating to Lavater's controversy with Nicolai. Includes exchange of letters between Elisa von der Recke and J.D. Uhlenhuth; her letter to Uhlenhuth is in a ms. copy and includes Tiedge's poem An Christus; also bound in are autobiographical notes by her and a fragment of an account of her return trip from Italy in the company of Tiedge and party. With typed manuscripts of all items.
  - LAVATER-WIELAND
    - Lavater, Johann Caspar, 1741-1801. 4 ALS to Christoph Martin Weiland, Zurich, 1775-76 (Box 2, Folder 141)
      14 p. The first letter chiefly concerns Matthias Claudius; mentions of Herder, the brothers Stolberg, Bahrdt, Bodmer, Lenz; the third and fourth letters contain a character sketch of Goethe, with mention of Werther, Wagner's Prometheus and Menschen, Thiere und Goethe
  - LETTERS TO HEINRICH HASE
    - Austin, Sarah Taylor, 1793-1868. ALS, London, 1836 Jul15 (Box 2, Folder 142)
      3 p. "Mrs. Austin begs to present to Dr. Hase a copy of her translation of his Griechische Alterthumskunde.."
    - Brühl, Karl Friedrich Moritz Paul, Graf von, 1772-1837. ALS, Seifersdorf, 1836 Aug 7 (Box 2, Folder 143)
      1 p. Theater director at the Berlin Hoftheater (1815-1828; later general director of the Berlin Museums
    - David d'Angers, Pierre Jean, 1788-1856. ALS, Zürich, 1836 Jul 20 (Box 2, Folder 144)
      3 p. In French. Sculptor. Mention of medallion of Böttiger, the bust of Rietschell, and the frieze for the Panthéon
    - Drummond. ALS (Box 2, Folder 145)
      1 p. In French. Acknowledgment of an invitation, written in the third person
    - Panofka, Theodor, 1800-1858. ALS, Berlin, 1838 Mar 15 (Box 2, Folder 146)
      1 p. Archaeologist. Sending a copy of his article Zeus and Aegina through two young archaeologists Dr. Kochen and Warren Molestadt
    - Schorn, Johann Karl Ludwig von, 1793-1842. ALS, Weimar, 1837 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 147)
      4 p. Art historian. Chiefly on the frescos in the chapel of S. Giorgo at Padua
    - Wach, Karl Wilhelm, 1787-1845. ALS (Box 2, Folder 148)
      1 p. Sending through Schadow, the Giotto'ssche Abendmahl and his respects to "Hofrath Bötticher" [i.e. C.A. Bötticher]
  - LETTERS TO GEORGE FRIEDRICH WALTHER
    - Fernow, Carl Ludwig, 1763-1808. ALS, Weimar, 1802 Jun 21 (Box 3, Folder 149)
      6 p. Art historian; librarian to the Duchess Anna Amalia of Saxe-Weimar- Eisenach. Concerns the edition of Winckelmann's works, 1808-20, of which Fernow edited v. 1-2; on p.4: "Goethe wird indessen auch von Carlsbad zurückommen, wo ich dann die versprochene Einleitung von ihm zu erhalten hoffe"; the publication appeared without a contribution from Goethe
    - Gaal, Georg von, 1783-1855. ALS, Wein, 1823 Sep 22 (Box 3, Folder 150)
      1 p. Suggesting a new enlarged edition of his poems for publication
    - Helvig, Anna Amalia (von Imhoff) von, 1776-1831. ALS, Dresden, 1821 Oct 6 (Box 3, Folder 151)
    - Reinhard, Franz Volkmar, 1753-1812. ALS, Dresden, 1795 Sep 2 (Box 3, Folder 152)
      2 p. As a new Dresdner Gesangbuch compiled by Wittman is ready for press, Reinhard is against the publication of a supplement to the existing Gesangbuch; also concerns the publication of the drafts of his sermons
    - Rossetti, Dominik, Elder von Scander, 1774-1842. ALS, Triest, 1818 Sep 29 (Box 3, Folder 153)
      2 p. Consul at Triest. Chiefly concerns a publication by Winckelmann.
  - FROM AND TO VARIOUS AUTHORS, A-Z
    - ALS to H. Velthausen, London Letter from Dresden, 1836 Mar 26 (Box 3, Folder 154)
      2 p. Signature illegible. Letter of recommendation, in German, for KGTW who is setting out on a trip to England
    - Börne, Ludwig, 1786-1837. ALS to Dresdner Abendzeitung, Frankfurt, 1818 Sep 23 (Box 3, Folder 155)
      1 p. Suggesting exchange of copies of a journal edited by him [probably Die Waage, Zeitschrift für Bürgerleben, Wissenschaft und Kunst] against copies of the Dresdner Abendzeitung. Manuscript note signed: Ch. Arnold, below this letter: Ich kann auf dieses Tauschgeschäft nicht eingehen. With a second manuscript note by Arnold: Wenn des Herrn D. Gebauers Schrift druckwürdig ausfällt, werde ich gern den Verlag davon übernehmen
    - Brandes, Johann Christian, 1735-1799. ALS to ?, Leipzig, 1777 Jun 6 (Box 3, Folder 156)
      3 p. Playwright, actor and theater director. Forwarding copies of pt. 1-2 of the Hamburgisches Theater with a request to distribute them to subscribers in Dresden
    - Bremer, Friedrika, 1801-1865. ALS to Marie Louise Förster, Stockholm, 1845 May 28 (Box 3, Folder 157)
      1 p. Letter of introduction for Miss Sophie Adlerspanne
    - Devrient, Eduard, 1801-1877. ALS to Max Maria Freiherr von Weber, 1857 Dec 11 (Box 3, Folder 158)
      1 p. Famous actor; producer at the Dresden Theater; later director of the court theater at Karlsruhe; playwright. Max was the son of Carl Maria von Weber; an expert and writer on railroads
    - De Wette, Wilhelm Martin Leberecht, 1780-1849. Autograph note, Berlin, 1817 Apr 12 (Box 3, Folder 159)
      1 p. Professor of Theology at Berlin and Basel. Attesting the attendance of his lectures on the Epistles of Paul by the student Koberstein
    - Eckermann, Johann Peter, 1792-1854. ALS to ?, Weimar, 1844 Mar 2 (Box 3, Folder 160)
      3 p. Submitting an article for a political newspaper. "Sagen Sie mal, wo stammt denn das dumme Gerücht her als ob ich Goethe's Secretair gewesen?"
    - Ende, Otto Baron von ALS to Robert Jameson, Dresden, 1836 Apr 28 (Box 3, Folder 161)
      2 p. Letter of introduction for Karl Gottfried Theodor Winkler who is coming to Edinburgh. Jameson was a mineralogist, professor of natural history at Edinburgh
    - Franz, Agnes, 1794-1843. 2 ALS to Dora Winkler, Breslau, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 162)
      4 p. Agnes Franz was an author of poetry, short stories and children's books. Dora Winkler was the daughter of KGTW
    - Gebler, Tobias Phillip Freiherr von, 1726-1786. ALS to ?, Wein, 1772 Apr 27 (Box 3, Folder 163)
      3 p. Austrian statesman; author of two works on Austrian tax law and of numerous plays which are collected in his Theatralische Werke, 1772-1772, 3v.
    - Gellert, Christian Fürchtegott, 1715-1769. ALS to Monsieur Zeis, Leipzig, 1754 Nov 23 (Box 3, Folder 164)
      3 p. Advice concerning his future
    - Gellert, Christian Fürchtegott, 1715-1769. ALS to Pastor Zeis, Leipzig, 1754 Dec19 (Box 3, Folder 165)
      3 p. Concerning a position as tutor for Zeis' son
    - Gleim, Johann Wilhelm Ludewig, 1719-1803. ALS to Christoph August Tiedge, Halberstadt, 1798 Aug 17 (Box 3, Folder 166)
      4 p. A severe rebuke for the sharp epistle Tiedge had written to Lorenz Benzler
    - Goedicke. ALS to Christoph August Tiedge, Berlin, 1818 Jun 27 (Box 3, Folder 167)
    - Goethe, Ottilie (von Pogwisch) von, 1797-1872. ALS to Finanzrath von Weber, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 168)
      1 p. An invitation to join her and Frau von Lemaiter
    - Hagedorn, Friedrich von, 1708-1754. ALS to ?, Hamburg, 1748 Sep 13 (Box 3, Folder 169)
      3 p. Indicating a choice of books, chiefly Italian, he wishes to acquire and giving detailed instructions for having them bound
    - Harrys, Georg, 1781-1838. ALS to Louisa Dulcken, Hannover, 1836 Apr 11 (Box 3, Folder 170)
      1 p. Letter of introduction for KGTW. Louisa Dulcken was a pianist at London
    - Houwald, Ernst Christoph Freiherr von, 1778-1845. Autograph greeting to ?, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 171)
      1 p. Author of poems, short stories and plays; friend of K.W.S. Contessa
    - Huber, Victor Aimé, 1800-1869. ALS to unidentified lady, 1845 Feb 22 (Box 3, Folder 172)
      1 p. Forwarding an issue of the periodical Janus of which he was the editor
    - Iffland, August Wilhelm, 1759-1814. ALS to Karl August Bötticher [i.e. Böttiger], Weimar, 1796 Apr 17 (Box 3, Folder 173)
      1 p. Actor, dramatist, theater director
    - Klein. ALS to Herr Hofgerichts- Assessor, Berlin, 1803 (Box 3, Folder 174)
      2 p. Discusses a treatise on evidence in crimes and the responsibility and guilt of the criminal
    - Körner, Christian Gottfried, 1756-1831. ALS to Christoph August Triedge, Dresden, 1814 Jan 10 (Box 3, Folder 175)
      4 p. Concerns the publication of his son's works, particularly Leyer und Schwert, which he hopes Tiedge will undertake to edit. Some poems Körner intends to publish as manuscript for his son's friends
    - Kügelgen, Gerhard von, 1772-1820. ALS to ?, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 176)
      1 p. Writes on behalf of Moritz von Engelhard in regard to a debt owed the addressee
    - Ligne, Charles Joseph, prince de, 1735-1814. ALS to ?, Wein, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 177)
      1 p. "Je vous prie, Messieurs, de garder cecy, sans le montrer personne, pour le faire imprimer à la Tête de mes ouvrages, dont je vous ai donné, je crois, la liste."
    - Manteuffel, Otto von, 1777-8112. ALS to Paul Thierot, Lübben, 1805 Feb 17 (Box 3, Folder 178)
      11 p. Mentions Jean Paul [Richter] and Schiller's death. Pages 6-[7] of another letter to Thierot written soon after March, 1805
    - Martin, Christoph Reinhard Dietrich, 1772-1857. ALS to ?, Heidelberg, 1812 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 179)
      2 p. Forwarding a copy of his Lehrbuch des deutschen gemeinen criminalprocesses. The addressee is active in the same field
    - Meier (H.H.) and Co., Bremen ALS to Baring Brothers and Co., London, 1836 May 16 (Box 3, Folder 180)
      1 p. Letter of introduction for KGTW
    - Meier (H.H.) and Co., Bremen ALS to Fred Huth and Co., London, 1836 May 16 (Box 3, Folder 181)
      1 p. Letter of introduction for KGTW in English
    - Mittermaier, Karl Josef Anton, 1787-1867. ALS to Christian Karl Stübel, Heidelberg, 1828 Aug 4 (Box 3, Folder 182)
      3 p. Mittermaier and Stübel were jurists
    - Morlacchi, Francesco, 1784-1841. ALS to Signor Tamburini, Dresden, 1836 Apr 28 (Box 3, Folder 183)
      2 p. A letter of introduction for KGTW who is coming to England. In Italian
    - Müller, Friedrich von, 1779-1849. ALS to ?, Weimar, 1844 Jan 10 (Box 3, Folder 184)
      4 p. Mentions a work by the recipient, entitled Magellan; discusses Goethe's house and collections and their administration by heirs
    - Puttrich, Ludwig, 1783-1856. ALS to Advocat Scarth, London, 1836 Apr 27 (Box 3, Folder 185)
      1 p. Puttrich was a jurist and art historian and collector. The letter being brought by KGTW on his trip to London, relates to a legal matter
    - Raumer, Friedrich Ludwig Georg von, 1781-1873. ALS to Professor Schäfer, Erlangen, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 186)
      1 p. Autograph note on verso, in another hand: Von Friedr. Raumer an Prof. Schäfer in Erlangen. Submitting a rough draft work on the teaching of history
    - Schmaltz, Moritz Ferdinand, 1785-1860. ALS to Senator Walther, Neustadt-Dresden, 1829 Jun 3 (Box 3, Folder 187)
      2 p. Thanking for the grant to the Frenzel family
    - Schröckh, Johann Matthias, 1733-1808. ALS to ?, Wittenburg, 1771 Nov 1 (Box 3, Folder 188)
      3 p. Historian. Concerns the publication in instalments, of a work by Schröckh
    - Schütze, Karl Heinrich Ferdinand. ALS to A.J. Droop, Dresden, 1826 May 19 (Box 3, Folder 189)
      1 p. Letter of introduction for KGTW, in English
    - Schütze, Karl Heinrich Ferdinand. ALS to David Low, Dresden, 1826 May 19 (Box 3, Folder 190)
      1 p. Letter of introduction for KGTW, in English. David Low was professor of agriculture at Edinburgh University
    - Schütze, Karl Heinrich Ferdinand. ALS to Effingham Wilson, Dresden, 1826 May 16 (Box 3, Folder 191)
      1 p. Letter of introduction for KGTW, in English. Schütze was a merchant with business connections in Hamburg and Philadelphia; in 1803 he established a business with a partner at London, from 1819 on he lived on his estate Schweta; assisted the foundation of a school for the poor in Dresden
    - Speck von Sternberg, Maximilian, freiherr von, 1776-1856. ALS to Edward Magrath, Leipzig, 1836 May 3 (Box 3, Folder 192)
      1 p. Letter of recommendation, in English, for KGTW who intends a trip to London. Magrath was secretary of the Athenaeum in London
    - Strauss, Johann Friedrich. ALS to the Abendzeitung, Ludwigsburg, 1825 Oct 31 (Box 3, Folder 193)
      2 p. Forwarding a poem by a 17 1/2 year old friend for publication in the Abendzeitung
    - Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice, prince de Bénévent, 1754-1838. 2 AL (copy) to the Duchess of Kurland, Paris, 1808 (Box 3, Folder 194)
      In French. Concerns the marriage of Talleyrand's son Edmond to Dorothea, the daughter of the Duchess of Kurland; it took place 1809. A (copy) of Tsar Alexander I of Russia to the Duchess Dorothea of Kurland, 1809 Jan 10, Petersburg, concerning the same matter
    - Thiersch, Friedrich Wilhelm von, 1784-1860. ALS to Curt von Querfurth, München, 1845 Jun 22 (Box 3, Folder 195)
      3 p. Philologist, educator and philhellene
    - Tiedge, Christoph August, 1752-1841. ALS to ?, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 196)
      1 p. A request from a friend (possibly KGTW) at the Dresden Theater for seven tickets to the opera Freischütz for the family Eberhard
    - Treuenfels, Franz Matthias Freiherr von, 1794-1828. ALS to ?, 1825 Jun 11 (Box 3, Folder 197)
      2 p. The author used Eduard von Stein as stage name; he appeared chiefly on the stages at Vienna and Leipzig
    - Unger-Sabatier, Karolina, 1805-1877. ALS to ?, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 198)